Today I'm excited to talk about bridging
informal and formal mathematical
reasoning with
AI.
And so probably throughout this course
um you've seen many different ways where
these AI agents can start to have a lot
of impact in different areas. And so one
interesting question is to what extent
can they impact more expert domains? So
say finance, science, medicine. and the
domain that I'll talk about today, which
is
mathematics. Now, with
mathematics, there's a variety of things
that you could imagine doing with an
agent or a language model. You could try
to have an open-ended dialogue with the
model. You could try to have it come up
with counter examples for you, help you
write proofs, and it's your imagination
is basically uh the limit.
Um and what I want to argue today is
that for math in particular, how you
represent the math is actually extremely
important to think
about. So one way to represent math is
what is called informal mathematics.
Here math is represented as raw data. So
it could be text, it could be an image,
it could be even audio if you're like
talking with someone about math. And
doing this is extremely flexible. And in
some sense, most of the math that you've
encountered or that you've used is
probably in some kind of informal
format. So even something like a latex
solution or an archive paper we would
consider to be informal.
Now when we think about using AI to
generate or operate in informal math
there is a really important problem
which is that we don't have any
guarantees that the math is correct or
not. So like here is an example of a
language model producing a solution and
the answer at the end is actually
correct but it makes these kind of
subtle mistakes in the intermediate
steps. And so for really simple math,
this might not actually be an issue and
the language model might still be
useful. But if we really want to trust
it in say education or in research level
math, then it could get very
tedious and very difficult to know
whether the outputs are correct or
not. So this motivates the other end of
the spectrum which is called formal
mathematics. Here math is written as
source code in a programming language
and basically the way it works is you
can write a specification or a lema or
theorem like 1 plus 1 equals 2 then you
can write a proof and the really cool
thing is that if all of the code
compiles then you have a formal
guarantee that the proof is
correct. And so this is a lot different
than the informal math because now we
can have certainty if say a language
model generates a proof that it is
actually a reliable and correct proof of
the
theorem. And there's been a variety of
these theorem proofing languages
developed. I'll mostly focus on a
language called lean which recently is
having a really exciting uh really
exciting growth and really exciting
intersection with the mathematical
community which I'll talk about in a
bit. And for one of the topics that I'll
talk about I'll also mention this
language called Isabel because it has
some features that make it kind of
amendable to writing different types of
proofs with AI systems.
So if you haven't seen one of these
before, um I wanted to actually show you
what one of these formal proof
assistants looked like. Um and so to do
this, we'll try to prove this really
simple theorem, uh which is like
transitivity. So if R is a subset of S
and S is a subset of T, then R is a
subset of
T. So um I'll actually show you this um
as a demo. And so here what I've done is
I've opened up VS code. And so as I
mentioned this is literally um like
programming like like writing code. And
here you could see the theorem
statement. Uh so if R is a subset of S
and S is a subset of T then R is a
subset of T.
And these are often called interactive
proof assistants because what happens is
as I go to write a proof, it actually
tells me over here what is the current
state of the proof. So the idea isn't to
learn every bit of the formal system,
but I'm kind of just showing you the
important parts that'll be relevant for
the talk. So here we can see these
different variables and we can see what
we have uh remaining to prove over here.
Now the thing is is that it takes some
expertise to actually write a proof in
lean. So for example if I know some lean
then one thing I can do is this command
here and you can notice that it actually
changed the state of the proof. So now I
have these two kind of variables up here
and the goal has also changed.
Then again if you have some expertise
then you can actually know that this
idea of
transitivity has already been programmed
uh into lean. So here I wrote this um
transitivity um rule here or or lema and
now you can see up here that it says
that there's no goals left. So I've kind
of completed the
proof. So we'll actually touch on a lot
of things that I've talked about here
throughout the talk. We'll talk about
the fact that it requires some expertise
to actually write a proof in one of
these proof
assistants. And if you look at this
proof, it might look a bit different
than one that you would see like written
down in a textbook or something like
that. So we'll revisit these ideas uh
throughout the talk.
So now going back to the talk
um we could ask like okay I showed you
this very simple example but is this is
this kind of toy or is this actually
useful for more complex
mathematics. So a really exciting thing
is that increasingly there's a larger
and larger intersection with the
mathematical community. So here's an
example of the mathematician Terrence
Tao and he formalized in lean the proof
of a theorem from one of his actual
papers and a really exciting thing
that's kind of playing into this is this
project which is called math lab. So if
you noticed in the demo I gave this idea
of transitivity was already kind of
programmed in and that's the idea of
math lab. So lots of people are
contributing and kind of building up
foundations that other people can use to
make it easier to write more and more uh
complex
math. And if you look at what
mathematicians write or or talk to them
and um listen to what they say then
these formal proof assistants are
exciting for a few different reasons. So
one is that they can potentially enable
a new form of
collaboration. So what you can do is you
can break down a kind of big problem or
big proof into multiple
pieces and then anyone can go on and
essentially submit code to try to solve
one of the pieces to say prove one of
the kind of helper theorems or helper
lemas. And then the cool thing is that
we know for a fact that we can trust the
code since lean will automatically check
it. And so this is a lot different than
the typical way of collaborating on say
a math paper where you kind of have to
trust the author or read through their
uh
results. It also gives you instant
feedback as we saw. So this could be
useful in a variety of ways including
when trying to learn math and of course
it has these guarantees on
correctness. So hopefully I've convinced
you that formal math is getting more and
more interesting for learning or for the
actual mathematical community. But why
is it actually important for AI? Well,
one thing is that as we all know, we are
not able to automatically check or trust
the outputs of AI models. And so what
the formal system gives us is some way
of just preventing incorrect math or it
turns out you can actually use this for
code as well.
Increasingly, we see more and more
models trained with reinforcement
learning. And I'll actually talk about
one of those in the talk. And what you
can think of the formal system as being
is it gives you this kind of perfect
reward signal of whether something is
correct or not correct. And this turns
out to be very useful for then improving
machine learning models further.
It also gets at one of the hot topics in
the field right now, which is reasoning.
And it gives you this nice playground
where you can try even very easy
reasoning problems to essentially
arbitrarily hard ones within the domain
of math.
And so if we look at the history of
language models in formal math, one of
the pioneering works happened in 2020
from these two authors from OpenAI and
they developed a system called
GPTF and so it actually used the
language model to kind of predict the
next steps of these
proofs and even back then they got some
pretty interesting results. So what they
did is they had the system uh generate a
proof and then they submitted it as a
pull request and here are some of the
comments from the kind of maintainers of
the formal proof library. Um even this
model back then could produce kind of
shorter proofs and some of them were
even philosophically uh more concise
than the human written
ones. And then since then we've seen
rapid progress in using methods based on
language models for formal theorem
proving. So here is showing the
performance on a really common
benchmark. These are based on math
competition problems. And I actually
made this plot a few months ago but it's
already out of date. Uh actually just
this morning there was a model released
that get like 80% on this benchmark.
And just to give you some flavor of what
these look like, again, you don't have
to read through the details of this or
through most of the examples I show in
this talk, but here's an actual um
output from a model called Deepseek
Prover. And it managed to produce this
proof of an IMO
problem. And so hopefully it gives you
some sense that the outputs of these are
starting to get pretty non-trivial.
And Terrence Tao, if we go back to
members of the mathematical community,
uh wrote that during his formalization
project, he was actually using GitHub
co-pilot and um sometimes was able to
like infer the directions he was going
on going in and things like that.
So with all this with formal math being
so exciting for both mathematics and for
AI the question is why don't people in
AI always use formal math? What is the
kind of blocker to making this happen?
So I want to argue that the key
challenge is that there's this gap
between how people are familiar with
doing math and the actual formal system.
In particular, there's just so many
ideas and intuitions and even the way
that we write proofs that are just
difficult or very tedious to express in
the formal system. In a formal system
like lean, each step of reasoning needs
to be explicitly spelled out in detail.
And as we saw even in that very simple
example that I gave, you often have to
have a deep knowledge of the system like
what things exist in the system and how
to write the code and so
on. And so the theme of this talk will
be steps towards bridging the gap
between informal reasoning and formal
reasoning.
Can we use AI and language models to get
the best of both worlds? Maintain the
flexibility of informal reasoning while
having all of these benefits that I
mentioned with operating in the formal
system. And so I'll talk about three
different directions that we and others
in the community are
pursuing. First I'll talk about
incorporating informal thoughts into the
formal theorem proving procedure.
I'll talk about training models to think
informally with reinforcement learning
and in particular our recent work which
is called lean
star. Then I'll move to informal provers
or informal proofs and I'll talk about
how you can break down the problem of
writing one of these proofs as first
writing a sketch and then kind of
filling in the lower level gaps of the
sketch. So I'll talk about our work
called draft sketch proof and then our
recent work which is actually not even
released yet of trying to enable tools
that let you fill in the gaps of these
sketches in the lean theorem
prover and then finally at the end of
the talk I will talk about more of a
future direction that we are taking
initial steps towards which is how do we
actually make these systems useful to
mathemat mathematicians doing research
level
mathematics. So in particular, I'll talk
about one way in which the models could
assist in these larger projects. I'll
talk about some tools that actually
already exist and you can try after the
talk if you want and a new benchmark
that tries to further progress of
building these assistants for these
complex research level type projects.
So with that let me go to the first part
where I will talk about uh integrating
informal thoughts into formal theorem
proving. So here this will largely be
based on um our paper called leanar
which we'll be presenting soon at
iclear and here again we're in the
setting of theorem proving uh in
lean. So here we have the theorem that I
showed you before at the top. And then
as I showed you in the demo, you could
think of this as a kind of interactive
step-by-step process. So in particular,
lean will give you this state of the
proof and then one thing that you could
do is you could send that state to a
language model and it could try to
generate the next step of the proof.
Then you can provide the next step to
lean and it can either tell you whether
the proof is is done, whether there is
an error or as we saw it can give you
the next state of the
proof. You could then continue this
until you either give up or you reach a
complete proof. And so in that sense,
you can see one of these proofs as being
a sequence of states and next steps or
they're called tactics.
So in a bit more detail, what we want to
do is train a model on some data set of
inputs and outputs. So an example is you
could have the model take in the proof
state and output the next step. And what
you typically do is you extract a lot of
these state and next step examples from
some corpus of theorems and proofs. So
for example, you could use the entire
math load project that I mentioned
earlier or you could even have a model
generate its own theorems and generate
its own proofs and then ultimately you
kind of turn it into a data
set. Once you've trained a model, you
then want to use it to generate full
proofs. So the traditional way of doing
this is through this kind of tree search
procedure. Here's an example tree search
called best first search. And basically
the idea is you ask the model to
generate multiple candidates for the
next
step. Then you somehow come up with a
score for each one of these
candidates. You choose the step with the
highest score. So for instance, first we
chose this uh intro H
step. Then you can expand those further.
choose the next highest scoring
sequence. As you can see here, it kind
of backtracked and then it took this
green path which led to a correct
proof. So this is just one possible
strategy you could use for generating a
full proof if your model can only
predict the next step.
So what we are interested in is can we
go beyond just training the model on
formal proofs and to generate formal
proofs and instead train the model to
think before each step of the formal
proof. So in particular we want to train
the model to generate what's on the
right where before taking a step it
outputs some reasoning and it's kind of
free to decide whatever it wants to do
with the reasoning. It could break down
the problem. It could plan out the next
step. It could even solve some
computation that isn't really present in
the formal
proof. So why would you want to do this?
Well, again, it could give the model
some room to plan out what it is about
to do. When you think about it, it can
help diversify the search space since
now the model is searching for proofs
not just in the formal space but in the
formal space augmented with these
thoughts. And I won't go into details
here, but there's been a lot of cool
work in the language model community
showing that adding in these kind of
chain of thought in other domains can
actually give a model which is more
expressive in terms of the kinds of
problems it can
solve. So we have a few good reasons to
try this out.
Now the key issue here is that nowhere
on the internet is there formal proofs
written in lean that have these nice uh
thoughts written out for them. And so
what we have to do is actually design an
algorithm so that a model kind of learns
on its own to produce these thoughts
that are useful for the proofs.
So the algorithm is called lean star and
it adopts this name from this other work
called self-taught reasoner and the
process basically has two different
phases. Um so the highle idea is we want
to learn to generate these thoughts via
reinforcement learning. So first we have
to initialize the model so that it can
produce some type of thoughts and then
we want to train it further so that it
gets better at using the thoughts to
prove theorems.
So in the first step we use this kind of
clever trick which is we can look at a
state and the actual next step of the
proof and then have a language model
just
retrospectively come up with some
thought that describes the transition
from the state to the next step. So what
we found is that if you don't give this
step then the language model might just
output a kind of meaningless or
incorrect thought but they were kind of
good enough at coming up with some
thought which described uh this
transition. So then we can annotate a
large set of proofs. So here for
instance we take all of math lab and we
can get like hundreds of thousands of
examples of of state thought and next
step. Then we can use that to train a
model and it doesn't necessarily have to
use um all 100,000 by the way for this
initial step. You want to just train
some initial model that knows to produce
these thoughts um prior to taking steps.
Then we want to take that model and put
it into this loop. So we have the model
generate full proofs. Then we ask lean
to tell us whether they are correct or
not. And then we use some type of
reinforcement learning algorithm to
improve the model
further. So what we need is some method
to generate proofs and we need to
actually choose some algorithm to
implement this with.
So what we discovered is that this
commonly used way of using the tree
search or best for search was actually
difficult to get to work when we added
in these thoughts. I think one reason is
that it gets difficult to actually
assign a really good score to the
thought and so as a result the tree
search kind of didn't work um as well.
So what we did is design a new method
which is this kind of simple idea of
generating multiple proofs in parallel.
So for a given trajectory you kind of
generate a step. If you get an error
from lean you just retry on that same
path and then you keep going up to a
maximum number of steps or if you reach
a you stop if you reach a complete
proof.
Then for the algorithm we actually just
used the simplest possible algorithm.
And so we as well as other groups are
now exploring more um better
reinforcement learning algorithms like
online algorithms. Um but here we did
something very simple which is you just
collect the successful trajectories you
add those to your data set and then you
train a new model um on this data set of
states thoughts and
tactics. So this algorithm goes by
various names. It's called expert
iteration. It's also called restdm. It's
also called rejection fine-tuning. But
the idea is very simple.
So then typically the way that these
models are evaluated is on these math
competition
problems. So although we train the model
on math lab, um here's a common test
data set which is used which is called
mini F2F. And here's an example problem
from the international math
olympiad. So here I've shown the
informal version just to show you what
the problem is like. But then the model
here only gets the formal version and
has to produce a
proof. So here are some results with an
early model that we tried in the
project. So in red you can see the model
that we started with and then in black
you could see the model after we perform
this initialization
step. Then in gray we can see the model
after we perform the expert iteration.
And you can see that the lean star
process basically took it from being
worse than this baseline model which was
based on this GPT4 agent to being better
than
it. Then at the end of the project we
applied lean star to the best available
base model at the time for theme
proving. And again we saw these
improvements um going from gray to
black. And at the time that we did this,
this was the kind of state-of-the-art
for this mini F2F data
set. One really interesting thing is
that we found that models with the
thoughts benefit more from scaling up
the search budget or the kind of
inference budget. So here we're seeing
as we sample more and more steps either
with our sampling method or as a
baseline with the best first search how
the performance uh looks and you can see
that the gains we get from the green
line which is lean star with the
thoughts are more pronounced than the
model that doesn't have the
thoughts. And so this might be
indicating the idea that I mentioned
before that adding in these thoughts
helps to kind of diversify the search
space. Here's some examples. And again,
you don't have to read through the
details, but if you're curious, you can
take a look at the paper after. One
interesting thing here is that if you
look at the formal code, there's
actually some steps of reasoning that
the model is doing in the informal
thought shown in gray that aren't really
present in the formal code.
And here's a longer example, partly
because it looks impressive, but also to
just show you that when you add in these
informal thoughts with the formal ones,
um the output starts to get um yeah,
fairly non-trivial.
So after lean star the really exciting
thing is that this idea of augmenting
models or reasoning models with thoughts
and training them with reinforcement
learning um has been adopted in the
theorem proving community. So in
particular uh very rapidly this idea of
incorporating thoughts became a part of
the state-of-the-art systems. So here's
the example that I mentioned before uh
called deepseek prover where they
incorporate in the informal thoughts and
then as I mentioned just this morning
there was this state-of-the-art prover
released by um this uh startup and you
can see that they have this idea of kind
of alternating between informal
reasoning and snippets of
code and then more broadly these
reasoning models that generate long
chains of thought and are trained with
reinforcement learning have really begun
to revolutionize the LM LLM reasoning.
So I'm not going to go into the details
here, but you have probably heard of
these models like OpenAI 01 and Deepseek
R1. And so it seems like at least
currently having this kind of informal
thinking is a really key part of the
reasoning
procedure. So to recap, Leanar kind of
builds on this observation that training
only on the formal code may be
insufficient to learn the actual thought
process that's needed to produce the
code. and it gives a kind of simple
algorithm for learning to generate the
thoughts. Now I'll move from informal
thoughts to informal provers and
informal proofs and in particular talk
about methods that prove theorems by
kind of producing this highle sketch and
then filling in the gaps of the sketch.
So here the motivation is to combine the
benefits of kind of higher level
reasoning and lower level
reasoning. And one motivation for this
is to think about like how do we
actually write one of these formal
proofs in the formal proof assistant uh
sorry informal proofs in the formal
proof assistant.
So again, you don't have to worry too
much about the details of of this, but
here we're trying to prove the statement
on the left. And what is notable here is
that we can somewhat break this informal
proof up into these three different
parts. Then it turns out that we can
write this in the formal system using
something that is structured kind of
analogously to the informal proof. So
this is a system called Isabel and it
has this style where you can write these
kind of intermediate claims or
conjectures and if you look at it they
somewhat line up with the different
steps like here you have 10 * 280
divided by 40 which shows up here and
then this is a way of basically writing
okay let's complete the proof.
Now the interesting thing here is that
you still need to produce a proof of one
of the of each one of these kind of
higher level steps. So that is shown in
green. And so you can see here that to
actually come up with that proof, it
doesn't really look like natural
languages at all. Here it's actually
calling this SMT solver and feeding it
some facts.
So interestingly we have this kind of
decomposition between high level and
these kind of lower level
things. So let me actually say a bit
more about how you produce these lower
level proofs uh in a system like
Isabel. So it turns out that there are
these very powerful and very useful
automation tools called hammers or this
one is called sledgehammer.
And the basic idea is that as you're
writing a proof as you know a human, you
could write one of these uh conjectures
and then you could call the
sledgehammer. What it does under the
covers is it calls out to external
automated provers, ones that are based
on first order logic or higher order
logic or SMT solvers.
And these turn out to be extremely
effective when you're using the system
for kind of yeah filling in these little
gaps of the
proof. What these are not good at is
let's say you want to solve an IMO
problem. Then the sledgehammer methods
just won't
succeed. The technical reason is that
based on how they're set up there is
just such a large search space of
possible proofs.
And in particular, if you think about
this proof as being structured as like
these have statements, they don't really
have the functionality to produce
statements like that. So in practice,
these are used kind of interactively as
you're writing a proof as a
human. So here the idea is we want to
combine some kind of highle prover with
a lower level prover like the
sledgehammer.
And this leads to our method which is
called draft sketch proof which we
presented in iClar in 2023 and uh
developed and released in late uh
2022. So here the idea is to come up
with this kind of three-step procedure.
First we're going to draft an informal
proof. Then we're going to translate it
into this formal sketch. And then we're
going to use a low-level prover to fill
in the gaps of the
sketch. So to show you this in more
detail, let's walk through each one of
these. So first we start off um with an
informal theorem and a formal theorem
statement. It's actually really
important to provide the system with the
formal theorem statement because when we
start to translate things, uh we want to
make sure that the model's not cheating
and it's actually
uh proving the thing that we wanted to
prove. Then in the first step we have
the system so it could be a human or it
could be an LLM generate some informal
proof. Then in the next step we have an
LLM translate the informal proof into
what's called a formal sketch. It's
essentially what I showed you before
except now we leave these gaps to be
filled which are the lower level
proofs. Then in the final stage we try
to close the gap with a lower level
prover. Here we are actually using the
sledgehammer tool that I told you about.
And if you're able to close all of the
gaps then you're guaranteed to have a
complete proof.
The interesting thing is that this
actually looks a lot different than what
I was showing you before where we have
this kind of step-by-step proof search
and maybe it's like a tree search. Now
what we can do is we can diversify the
search space by just generating many
possible informal proofs or
drafts and or generate many potential
translations of those into formal
sketches and then we can just try to
fill in the gaps. And if the gaps are
filled in any of the sketch sketches,
then we have a formal proof that we
could consider as the output of the
system. So here's showing what happens
as we scale up the number of calls to
the pipeline. So here we're either
generating many informal proof drafts or
in the case of using a human written
informal proof we're generating many
possible translations into the formal
sketch.
You could see on the left hand side that
if we just call the system once then it
actually I mean it proves some things
but it's not very good and we really see
the benefits as we scale up the amount
of proof search or sampling and up here
we're proving a large number of
problems. This is on the same mini FTF
data
set. Now this was in the days of codeex
and manurva if you remember those
models. And interestingly here if you
look on the very right hand side if we
actually sampled enough from the model
then we were able to right at the end
surpass the performance of using a human
written proof. And so this was kind of
exciting and probably now that language
models are much better we would be able
to um make that transition uh even
earlier.
So here's an example of proving an
international math Olympia problem. So
here the language model produces the
informal proof shown in green. Then the
language model produces the formal
sketch shown in blue. You can see that
here we actually um back then even had
these informal kind of thoughts in as
comments. Um or here it's show showing
the informal version of the
step. Um, and then we have the
sledgehammer system fill in the gaps
shown in purple. And you can see that
sometimes it's pretty non-trivial. Like
here again, it's calling this SMT solver
and feeding in a bunch of different, uh,
facts or
premises. So since then, um, I've put
together a tutorial for, um, theorem
proving. So, it goes over the kind of
step-by-step methods that I mentioned in
the first part and also has a notebook
that shows you how to implement this
draft sketch proof method. And in
particular, it just calls out to a
language model API. So, you can try it
out with one of the any state-of-the-art
model uh that you want to if you're
curious to to learn more.
So to recap, I talked about this method
called draft sketch proof which
generates these highle sketches and then
tries to fill in the gaps. And what this
relied on is in this language Isabel
having this lower level prover called
sledgehammer. So next I'm going to talk
about our very recent work on trying to
build one of these sledgehammer uh
provers for lean so that we can more
easily write these kind of sketchbased
uh proofs in
lean. So this is based on a paper that
is um uh still not public which is
called premise selection for a lean
hammer where we build a system called
lean hammer.
So what is a hammer? So a hammer
integrates as I mentioned these external
provers and there's a bit of terminology
here that is a bit tricky if you haven't
seen the distinction before. Um
specifically what it does is it
integrates an automated theorem prover
into an interactive theorem
prover. So an interactive theorem prover
is the like the one I showed you like
lean and and essentially it's a
programming language that is able to
check the
proofs. However, the language on its own
doesn't give you a way of automatically
producing the proofs. You usually have
to write them as a human.
An automated theorem prover is something
that tries to automatically find proofs
and traditionally these are based on
different kinds of logics. So they might
be based on higher order logic provers
or things like SMT
solvers. And so as I mentioned before,
these automated theorem provers really
struggle with more complex um uh proofs
due to this large search space in their
kind of
formalism. So what we can do to try to
help with this problem is to solve this
really important problem which is called
premise selection.
So basically what you do is you provide
the automated theorem prover with many
different facts. So you can provide it
with you know definitions different
theorems different lemas and then it
goes off and tries to prove the um the
theorem that you
want and if we look at the number of
premises in say lean's math lab then
it's extremely large so it's you know
hundreds of thousands of
premises and so if you just give all of
those to the automated theorem prover it
will really struggle because
um it has this uh really large search
space. So the basic idea of premise
selection is to somehow cut down the
number of premises that we give uh and
only provide it ones that are likely to
be useful for proving the
theorem. So then we can look at what is
the typical hammer
pipeline. So here it is at a kind of
high level. Let's say we're in lean.
Then we start off with the thing we want
to prove on the
left. Then we would pass it to some kind
of premise selection
system. Now once we've selected premises
like definitions and and theorems, we
have to translate it from lean into the
language of the automated theorem
prover. Let's say that the automated
theorem provers a complete proof. Well,
then we have to actually translate it
back into a lean proof.
And so the way that that's done is
through the step which is called proof
reconstruction. So it basically takes
the output and tries to produce a proof
uh in lean. Then as our output we would
see this uh nice proof on the left on
the right
sorry.
So amazingly there's been a lot of
really cool work in the community on
these different parts.
Usually they're developed somewhat
independently of each other, but we have
this uh translation layer called lean
auto
um that can translate from that can help
translate from lean's dependent type
theory into um the higher order logic.
An example automated theorem prover is
called zipper position. And then for
this proof reconstruction, uh this was
developed by uh Josh Clint and
collaborators who's part of this lean
hammer project. Um and there's a system
called uh
duper. So what we're interested in here
is two different things. First, we want
to try to solve this premise selection
problem. And then second, we have to
come up with some way of actually
combining these together. When I show it
on a slide, it looks kind of simple to
put them together, but it's actually not
clear what the best way to do this is.
And even more, we want to kind of go
beyond the standard pipeline, uh, which
I'll talk about in a
bit. So, first let me talk about the
premise
selection. What we do is to frame this
as retrieval with a neural language
model.
So in particular we have a kind of
standard retrieval setup here. We embed
our input. So this will be the goal that
we want to prove and we have a language
model that produces this embedding shown
on the
right. Then we embed all of our
potential premises. So this will include
theorems, definitions, lemas and they
could be from math lab. They could also
be local premises in your project or uh
the in the hypothesis that you're going
to prove. And with that we get this list
of um embeddings shown on the
right. Then to select the premises we
take the dotproduct uh use cosine
similarity to select the set of uh
highest ranked premises.
So here we train with this contrastive
loss that is often used to train
retrieval models. So it boils down to
collecting these inputs, the states as
well as some positive premises and
negative premises.
And it turns out that there's actually a
lot of nuance in how to do this
properly, especially when the output is
going to be this lean auto uh sorry when
the interface is with this lean auto
system in the hammer pipeline. So I
won't go into all the details here and
when we release the paper it will have
all the details but even things like how
you how and whether you simplify terms
um how exactly you choose these positive
premises and negative premises turn out
to have a large impact on behavior on on
the um behavior of the retriever. And so
we'll show in the results in a second
that based on some previous retrievers
that were trained um our system that we
trained um does a lot better when we put
it into this hammer
pipeline. So then the question is how do
we combine all of these different
pieces? And so what we did is not just
have this kind of linear picture that I
showed on the previous slide, but we
actually incorporate these components
into a tree search.
So there's a really cool tree search
method and it's this kind of symbolic
tree search called
ASOP and yeah it does this um tree
search over different uh tactics or
steps of the proof. And so what we do is
kind of wire it up so that it can use
the selected premises to call different
tactics in
lean and it can at any time query this
automated theorem prover using the
selected premises. And so this step will
involve the translation that I mentioned
as well as the proof reconstruction.
So now with all of these different parts
that I've described, uh you could say um
how how is this actually useful as a
user? Well, um it turns out that we can
wrap this all into one kind of simple
command. So at any step of a proof, um
you can just call this hammer tactic and
then it'll run this tree search that I
mentioned. um you know call the external
prover and all that and then if it
succeeds it will display the proof to
you uh on the
right. And what's cool about this is you
could potentially enable this kind of
sketchbased proofing that I was talking
about before. So here I want to show an
actual um demo of the system where we
took a human written proof sketch from
this textbook mathematics and lean uh
and we want to try to fill in the gaps
with the uh hammer
system. So this theorem is the um
irrationality of the square root of two.
Um and yeah, sometimes in the formal
system you'll write it in a slightly um
different way, but the yeah, the the the
details are not too important for the
demo, but you can kind of read through
uh after if you
want. So here we'll um we'll go back
into uh VS code and here is first of all
the simple um theorem that I showed you
before.
And so what we can do is we can um call
this
hammer. And um the first time you run it
should take um a few seconds. And so
what it's done is it's selected the
premises and called the um the the um
the tree search and all that. And now
you can see that it came back with this
uh proof this uh theorem or lema.
So this one just says that um if 2
divides m^2 then uh 2 will divide m. So
it turns out that this one will actually
be useful in this uh irrationality proof
below. So now we can go step by step and
try to uh fill in the gaps with the
hammer.
Um, so here it got this one and we can
just keep
going. And interestingly up here it
actually used the lema that we just
proved. So you can see two divide of two
divide
square. Um, and so here it succeeded
again. And I'll just keep going for fun.
So the the idea here is that um by doing
this you don't necessarily have to worry
about these different details. So here's
a kind of interesting one where it's
actually calling the automated theorem
prover. Um so you can see all the
different facts that are being passed to
it. And here we could see the call um
the actual call to duper. Uh so duper
was this like proof reconstruction
method that I mentioned uh before. So if
you want you could treat this as the
proof or you can just leave this one in
there. Um for this step you actually
have turns out you have to do this one
step of clearing out this
hypothesis. Um, but then you can call it
the
hammer. And um, just for fun, I'll
finish off this uh, this proof just to
show you that it's um, that it's
possible. Okay. And then here's the last
step and we can call the hammer.
Okay, so now we have a complete proof of
the theorem and we started off with
these kind of highle steps and we're
able to um kind of fill in the
gaps. So um again here's the kind of uh
summary and um then what we could do is
evaluate this with different premise
selectors uh swapped in. So here's some
results on um theorems that we held out
from math lab as a kind of test set and
we just run the hammer at the first step
of the proof. So on the left here you
could see what happens if you don't have
the premise selection.
Um then here is using a um retriever
that was uh from prior work. What we did
is we retrained it on the exact same um
snapshot of Mathlib. So it had kind of
up-to-date data and it's partially
showing that like the specific decisions
that we make in training our retriever
um were really important for
performance. Interestingly, there's a
symbolic premise selection system. I
believe it's based on the one that was
in the Isabel sledgehammer. Um, so Kim
Morrison from the lean community um
reimplemented it in lean and you can see
that it actually does pretty um pretty
decently when it's in our hammer
pipeline. Here is the lean hammer
retriever um as the fourth bar with the
kind of diagonal lines. And then
interestingly it ends up being
complimentary to the symbolic um meo
retriever. So you could see with these
kind of cross-hatch lines, uh, you get a
performance boost if you just take the
union of
premises. And then in absolute terms,
it's starting to get pretty good. So all
the way on the right is the performance
that we get if we just use the ground
truth premises that um occur in the
human proof. And you can see that the
performance is starting to approach um
the performance that we get if we use
those. Um so to recap, I talked about
two different approaches for um
combining informal and formal provers or
even formal informal proofs. Um I talked
about draft sketch proof which involves
drafting an informal proof um generating
a formal sketch and then filling in the
low-level
details. And I talked about lean hammer
which is trying to bring this kind of
paradigm to lean or make it easier. So
in particular we try to build this
hammer and it involves this neural
premise selection and a tree search and
calling out to the automated theorem
prover and one uh interesting takeaway
from this is I didn't go into detail of
the model that we trained but the
largest model that we trained was just a
100 million parameter retriever so very
small and as you maybe saw in the demo
you can get some pretty non-trivial
behavior um or performance from
integrating it in. So it's kind of
exciting because yeah in these cases
even these fairly small by today's
standards neural networks can be uh
fairly powerful.
So in the last part of the talk I want
to talk about um trying to use AI or
techniques that I've talked about to
actually assist in research level
mathematics. So, not just prove the um
IMO problems, but try to help out in
these more complex pro uh projects that
um mathematicians or if you're a kind of
like lean um hobbyist or interested in
formalizing something
difficult. So, what does it actually
look like to formalize research level
math? Well, here we can look at this
blog post that was written by Terrence
Tao and he kind of breaks down the steps
that were involved in formalizing a
proof from this paper which is shown on
the
left. So again the goal was to take one
of the main theorems from the paper and
then try to write it in lean and come up
with a formal proof. And the first step
is to write what is called a blueprint.
So here you kind of go step by step and
think about how would this proof
decompose into different definitions
into different lemmas and ultimately uh
we can come up with the kind of final
theorem and proof that we care about.
And as you can see here on the top it's
showing a kind of dependency graph of
all of these theorems and all of these
definitions. So it gets fairly complex
and at the very bottom you have the
final theorem and final
proof and so interestingly here
everything is still written in informal
language. So you could see here the
theorem and the proof uh just written in
latte and then you try to think about
okay how do we actually realize this in
lean and so what it comes down to is a
large set of these formal definitions
and formal lemas and and formal theorems
and then ultimately you're able to kind
of state your final theorem and write
the proof of
it. So at the end you have this proof
and this theorem that are really
dependent on this kind of graph of
things that I showed
you. So a question is like at what point
of this procedure could AI
help? So maybe at least for now we don't
have it do this whole pipeline end to
end but we could think about like what
is the simplest thing that we could have
it do and that we could have kind of uh
trust. So one thing you could do is you
could look at this blueprint and look at
just one of these kind of theorems or
lemos that is um kind of necessary for
the proof but is just one part of it.
So here's an example where we have this
lema which occurs somewhere in here and
if we give this to a language model and
it produces a proof then again we can
kind of trust the output because lean
has checked it and in some sense it's
helped the development because then the
um human proof writer doesn't have to
kind of go go through this
step. So in order to do this um we
really have to overcome two uh at least
two different gaps that um that
occur. The first I'll call the
accessibility gap and this is just the
kind of simple observation that a lot of
times these methods are developed but
then they're actually hard to integrate
into actual tools. So for example, the
system might be very capable, but it
might not be open source or the results
might be very impressive, but then
they're actually very expensive or
costly to run. And so when you think
about this kind of practical setting, it
adds constraints onto the methods that
you have to develop.
But luckily we actually do have some
tools already available that could
potentially be useful for these kind of
simple
gaps. Um so we developed one of them
called LLM lean and you could go
download it and and use it um right now
if you want. And so the basic idea is to
just create this interface between lean
and some language model.
So what it does is it gives you these
different uh commands or tactics. Uh
like this one queries a language model
to try to produce the next step of the
proof. And then we can actually check
the outputs of the model. So we could
discard the incorrect ones and just
display ones that kind of finish the
proof. Those are shown in green or blue
ones are ones that kind of don't give an
error but don't necessarily uh finish
the proof.
And um in particular you can uh even
nowadays have a model running on your
laptop. So there's these different
libraries that have been developed uh
like Olama or LM Studio and you could
basically host the language model on
your laptop and then use LLM lean to
communicate with
it. Similarly you can have it
communicate with um some API. So it
could be open AAI, it could be claude,
Gemini, um,
together.AI. And so now you can actually
try to use these models to give you
suggestions that are checked and
lean. So as the last demo, I wanted to
um just uh show you this
um and so let's look for the other
window.
Okay, so let's go back to this really
simple theorem that I showed at the
beginning of the
talk. Um, and you probably you might
have noticed that I imported this lm
lean here. And so now we could call this
lm step uh command that I
showed and actually comes up with this
uh intro command that I showed you at
the beginning of the
talk. Then we could call it um again
And in this case it um yeah was able to
finish the
proof. Um so another thing you can do is
you can you could say like try to just
do this exact command. So try to prove
it in one step. Um it actually came up
with this
um bit more clever kind of one-step uh
proof. Uh there's another command that
just tries to prove it um in end to end
uh pro like fully prove it instead of
just predicting the next
step.
Um so here the model comes up with um
yeah multiple potential uh proofs and
you can see they're a bit different
style maybe um bit
longer. So you can also do other like
fun things like um shorten this
proof and put it as
a comment and then call the
lmqd. So let's see what it does. And
yeah, so now it gives us some options
that are shorter. Actually, this is
pretty short. You could just prove it in
kind of one call.
Um so yeah this is a tool that you could
use um today you just need to uh you
know have a language model API um and
then um yeah you can import it into uh
to a lean
project. Um so interestingly
um let's see here the methods are still
bottlenecked obviously by how good the
model is at uh proving theorems. Um but
like even now um I kind of went through
Terrence TA's project this PFR project
and just picked a file and um yeah this
one was actually able to fill in some of
these uh um yeah small small lemas. This
was actually the example that I showed
you before uh on the previous slide.
So another thing is I mentioned that the
models right now are the kind of
bottleneck right we have the interface
set up and so now it just comes down to
whether the model can complete um
theorems that occur in these kind of
kinds of
projects. So this leads to a second kind
of gap which is the gap in the way that
we benchmark these theorem proving
models. So largely these models are
benchmarked on their ability to prove
these math competition problems like
ones from the
IMO. And what these problems have is
they're fairly self-contained. Um so you
can usually state the problem in just
like one line of code. And then they're
kind of designed to somewhat use
standard results. Um so there's a kind
of standard set and you know a lot of
them have been implemented in math lib
and then constructing the proof is very
difficult. It requires a lot of
creativity but it's kind of relying on
these uh standard
results. If we compare that to this
project that I've been telling you
about, these have these complex
dependencies from throughout the
project. So in particular, um this
theorem to even state it or to prove it,
it might actually rely on these brand
new definitions and brand new lemmas
that have been created for the project.
And so unless we like continually train
the model on all of the current
projects, it really has to learn to
prove theorems in this kind of context
dependent setting that I'm showing on
the
right. So this leads to our um new
benchmark called mini CTX or mini
context. And we'll also be presenting
this at iClar as an oral presentation.
So here what we do is we made this
observation that I just told you about
that when we look at these real these
kind of research level or actual
formalizations that people do in lean
they are really in this context
dependent setting where you want to
prove a theorem and it depends on like a
whole repository of code new definitions
or new auxiliary
lemos. So the idea of the benchmark is
to test models on actual real lean
projects. So in particular we choose
some date cutoff and then we look at a
project like math lab and we can take
all of the theorems that were developed
after that
date. Similarly we can look at when a
project was created and take theorems um
and kind of contexts from those
different projects. So this PFR project
by um Terrence Town and collaborators
that I've been telling you about is like
one of the projects that was in the
first version of this uh
benchmark. Then the idea is we also make
tools so that you can automatically
extract benchmark problems from these
projects. So what you can do is update
the benchmark to kind of stay ahead of
the training cutoffs for these language
models. So we've actually already
released a mini CTX uh version two and
it has kind of more recent pro um lean
projects that have been developed like
in the past couple of months.
So here we have two different types of
contexts and um these are basically like
what dependencies are needed to prove a
theorem and what we do is we build
tooling to automatically extract um
things like
dependencies and um so and we can look
at like does a theorem depend on things
just in the current file or does it
depend on things across multiple files.
And then we can also get things like you
know what are the set of available
premises when you're going to prove this
theorem. So kind of very realistic
setting. So in particular let's look at
two different settings. One setting is
where all of the dependencies just
appear in the current file. Uh and then
the other is when the dependencies can
span multiple files.
So the first thing we want to do is
actually demonstrate that this context
actually
matters. So again I've told you about
this really common way of training uh
theorem provers which is by just giving
them the proof state and then having
them produce a next step or having them
kind of produce thoughts if you want.
So here what we did is um develop this
simple baseline method which
additionally gives the model all of the
code in the file uh so far. So this can
include like new definitions uh new
lemas even like new notation or natural
language comments and we wanted to see
how this compared to just taking in the
proof state.
So interestingly, if you look at a
competition problem data set like mini
F2F, it actually really doesn't matter.
You can do pretty similarly whether you
take in additional context. It would
just be like the import statements for
mini F2F um or if you just take the
proof state. So this might be one reason
why a lot of these state-of-the-art
theorem proving methods don't really um
deal with or support any kind of
external
context. However, when we evaluate them
on um our benchmark mini CTX which has
the um theorems from real real world
projects, we can see this dramatic gap
in the
performance. And the reason is pretty
obvious if you just look at a lean file.
It's because in these real projects
you're defining these kind of new
definitions and new lemmos like I
discussed. Interestingly, um you can
also do this uh premise selection and
kind of give the language model the
premises. Um and you can see variations
on based on whether the theorem requires
just infile information or out of file
information.
Um so all the way on the left we have
theorems with um very low
dependencies. The first set of bar
graphs shows um high dependencies on
infile premises. And so here you could
see that you do pretty well by just
giving the language model all the code
in the current file. And then in the
third set of bar graphs you see what
happens when we have these cross file
dependencies. And you can see that
adding in this premise selection uh
leads to some
improvement. So here we are using a um
an older premise selector system. So
we're excited about like integrating our
uh lean hammer into this for addressing
the cross file dependencies. Uh and in
general there's a kind of wide space of
methods that could be developed um for
this setting.
Um, so I should also mention that we um
provide the model with this file tuning.
So it's trained to take in the file
context um through O Lama. So you can
like download it, run it on your laptop
and use it inside of
Lean. Um, and then all of the methods
that are in LLM lean that are calling
the proprietary language models or the
API based ones. Um, they'll actually
prompt the model with all of the code in
the current
file. Um, and then as I mentioned
everything from the project is open
source. So the data, the models, um our
data extraction tool and uh even the um
evaluation code which is like a wrapper
of the lean uh ripple and so you can
check out those resources um
online. Um so as I mentioned in this
third part if we look at um these kind
of real lean projects or what it would
take to formalize research level math it
opens up some unique challenges. Uh
these aren't the only challenges of
course but uh two that are really
present in the kind of research
community right now. One is that we
still have a gap between the AI advances
and tools that people can use. And then
second, the benchmarks don't always
reflect all of the capabilities that are
required to do this real world
formalization. And so this is very much
an open research direction. And as I
mentioned, this benchmark is kind of the
the first
step. So in summary, in this talk, I
talked about three different ways to try
to bridge informal and formal
mathematical reasoning. I talked about
incorporating informal thoughts by
training models to think
informally. I talked about incorporating
informal provers or informal uh proofs
through methods that sketch proofs and
try to fill in the gaps. And then
towards the end I talked about trying to
take say a research paper and look at
what is involved in producing a formal
version of it and looking at what are
some initial ways where AI can help in
the
process. And so with that that is all I
have for today's talk. And I'd like to
thank um all of the amazing
collaborators on these various works. Um
they're listed here. And again, my name
is uh Sean and I have my email address
here.